Albert Watson II Papers
Albert Watson II Papers
1964-1966
Watson, Albert, 1909-1993.
3.0 linear feet
Lieutenant General, United States Army, High Commissioner of the Ryukyu Islands, 1964-1966. Collection contains correspondence, 1964-66; news clippings, 1964-66; press releases, 1964-66; and photographs, 1964.
148736
Biographical History
Albert Watson II (1909-1993) was a Lieutenant General in the United States Army. A graduate of the U.S. Military Academy, he rose through the ranks, serving in Hollandia, Hawaii, Lezte, Okinawa and Japan during World War II, and from 1950 to 1953 was on the faculty of the Army War College. He was a corps commander in the Korean War and afterwards returned to Washington to serve on the Army General Staff from 1955 to 1958. He then served as Commanding General of the 24th Infantry (1958-1960), of the Third Infantry (1960-1961), of the Third U.S. Army in Berlin (1961-1963), and of the IX Army Corps (1964-1966). While in the latter position, his last prior to retirement in 1966, he was also High Commissioner of the Ryukyu Islands in the Japanese archipelago.
His awards and decorations include the Legion of Merit, Bronze Star, Army Commendation Ribbon, and Distinguished Service Medal.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Albert Watson II Papers contains material relating to Watson's tenure as High Commissioner of the Ryukyu Islands. The collection consists of correspondence (outgoing only), one subject file (photocopies of Watson's appointment as High Commissioner), clippings (about Watson and the Ryukyu Islands), press releases and photographs of Watson and others.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence, clippings and press releases are arranged chronologically. Other material is in no particular order.
Related Material
See also the
Norman D. King Papers
for more Ryukyu material.
also has a large collection of published material relating to the Ryukyu Islands area. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Politics, government and public administration; Watson, Albert, 1909-1993.; Ryukyu Islands (United States Civil Administration, 1950-1972). -- Office of the High Commissioner.; United States. -- Army -- Officers.; United States -- Foreign relations -- 20th century.; United States -- Relations -- Pacific Area.; Military history -- United States.; Ryukyu Islands -- History -- 1945-1972.; Ryukyu Islands -- Relations -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Press releases.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Albert Watson II, 1965.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Appointment papers (photocopies), 1964 (Box 1)
- Newspaper clippings
  - Miscellaneous, Apr 1964-Mar 1965; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, Apr 1965-Oct 1966; 6 folders (Box 2)
- Press releases
  - News releases, U.S. Civil Administration, Ryukyu Islands, 1964-1966; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - News summaries, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Okinawa Press Highlights, U.S. Civil Administration, Ryukyu Islands, 1964-1966; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Okinawa Press Translations, U.S. Civil Administration, Ryukyu Islands, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Press conferences, 1964-1966; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Speeches, 1964-1966 (Box 5)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous, 1964; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1965-1966; 5 folders (Box 6)